That day, I encountered
Hari itu, aku bertemu
a small rabbit and my own instincts.
seekor kelinci kecil dan naluriku.
Are you seriously going to eat your classmate?
Kau serius akan makan teman sekelasmu?
We took classes together.
Kita sekelas.
Are we nothing but food to you carnivores?
Apakah kami cuma makanan bagi kalian karnivora?
LECTURE OVERVIEW MUTUAL UNDERSTANDING BETWEEN SPECIES
KILASAN MATA PELAJARAN PEMAHAMAN TIMBAL BALIK ANTARA SPESIES
You carnivores are all monsters!
Kalian karnivora semua monster!
Extra!
Surat kabar!
Extra here!
Surat kabar di sini!
Devoured?
Dilahap?
Did you hear? It was Tem from the drama club.
Kau sudah dengar? Itu Tem dari klub drama.
No way.
Tak mungkin.
Els, he was in your club.
Els, dia di klubmu.
We rehearsed together yesterday.
Kami berlatih bersama kemarin.
The killer has to be one of the carnivorous students.
Pembunuhnya pasti salah satu siswa karnivora.
We don't know if it was a student yet.
Kita tak tahu apakah itu siswa.
But it definitely was a carnivore.
Tetapi jelas karnivora.
I'm sorry to say this, but it's pretty ironic
Maaf kukatakan ini, tetapi ironis
that a drama student became the prey.
bahwa siswa drama jadi mangsa.
The drama club was known for its friendship
Klub drama dikenal atas persahabatan
between carnivores and herbivores.
antara karnivora dan herbivora.
Be careful, Els.
Hati-hati, Els.
Isn't there a gray wolf in the club?
Bukankah ada serigala kelabu di klub?
Gosh, I lost my appetite.
Astaga, aku kehilangan selera makan.
Me, too.
Aku juga.
HERBIVORES TODAY'S SPECIAL: SEAFOOD VEGGIE PLATE
HERBIVORA MENU HARI INI: SAYURAN DAN MAKANAN LAUT
This is bad.
Ini buruk.
Yeah. We have our show in two weeks.
Ya. Drama kita dua pekan lagi.
We need to find a replacement for Tem.
Kita harus cari pengganti Tem.
Yeah.
Ya.
But should we really be performing when one of our members just died?
Tetapi apa kita harus tampil saat satu anggota kita tewas?
I still can't believe it.
Aku masih tak percaya.
Yeah.
Ya.
Where are Rouis and the seniors?
Di mana Rouis dan para senior?
They're having a club meeting.
Mereka rapat klub.
What's wrong, Els?
Ada apa, Els?
Well...
Begini...
Is everyone here?
Semua sudah lengkap?
Gather around.
Berkumpullah.
SHOW NOT YOUR FANGS BUT YOUR HEART
JANGAN TUNJUKKAN TARINGMU TETAPI HATIMU
I'm sure you already know,
Pasti kalian sudah tahu,
but a horrible incident happened at school this morning.
insiden buruk terjadi di sekolah pagi ini.
Tem, the actor...
Tem, aktor...
President!
Ketua!
This is the only place Tem was in contact with the carnivores.
Cuma di tempat ini Tem berhubungan dengan karnivora.
And?
Dan?
Are you suspecting us?
Kau mencurigai kami?
Maybe someone got jealous of him for getting a good role.
Mungkin ada yang iri dengannya karena dapat peran bagus.
How dare you say that!
Beraninya kau berkata begitu!
Herbivores are always like this.
Herbivora selalu seperti ini.
Wanna start a fight?
Mau berkelahi?
-I can't open these walnuts. -If a carnivore hurts a herbivore...
- Kacang tak bisa kubuka... - Jika karnivora sakiti herbivora...
-Where's Legoshi? -...they would be expelled.
- Mana Legoshi? - ...akan dikeluarkan.
-Hey. -Ridiculous!
- Hei. - Konyol!
-Legoshi isn't a nutcracker. -You're not even worth using my fangs.
- Legoshi bukan pembuka kacang. - Kau tak layak gunakan taringku.
-Stop it! -You're right.
- Hentikan! - Kau benar.
-You're both stripes. -Legoshi isn't here.
- Kalian bergaris. - Legoshi tak ada.
Where has he gone?
Dia pergi ke mana?
I'm scared.
Aku takut.
Those were eyes looking at prey.
Itu mata yang menatap mangsa.
That wolf's telling me that I'm next.
Serigala itu berkata aku berikutnya.
You're overthinking.
Kau berpikir berlebihan.
Legoshi's always been a bit weird.
Legoshi selalu agak aneh.
You can come see me anytime.
Kau bisa temui aku kapan saja.
We prosimians are always fun and cheerful.
Kita prosimian selalu ceria dan asyik.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
Good night.
Selamat malam.
Stay away.
Menjauhlah.
You pretend to be our friend, but once you're hungry, we're your food?
Kau pura-pura jadi teman kami, tetapi saat kau lapar, kami makananmu?
Don't look down on us!
Jangan meremehkan kami!
Tem and I are much more...
Tem dan aku lebih dari...
Here.
Ini.
It's a love letter. For you.
Surat cinta. Untukmu.
I waited so we could be alone.
Aku menunggu agar kita bisa berdua saja.
TO ELS, FROM TEM
UNTUK ELS, DARI TEM
You wanted to give me this?
Kau mau memberiku ini?
Yeah.
Ya.
I knew Tem couldn't give it to you.
Aku tahu Tem tak bisa memberikannya kepadamu.
Sorry.
Maaf.
Maybe I shouldn't have done this.
Mungkin aku tak boleh lakukan ini.
It's okay. Thank you.
Tak apa-apa. Terima kasih.
Well, see you tomorrow.
Sampai besok.
Hey.
Hei.
I said something really mean earlier.
Aku mengucapkan hal yang jahat tadi.
You're a kind wolf.
Kau serigala baik.
I'll take it back tomorrow.
Akan kukembalikan besok.
So forgive me, please?
Jadi maafkan aku?
You don't need to take it back.
Kau tak perlu kembalikan.
Why?
Kenapa?
If everyone finds out about his first love after he died,
Jika semua tahu soal cinta pertamanya setelah dia tewas,
I'd feel bad for Tem.
aku kasihan dengan Tem.
But still...
Tetap saja...
If I don't do anything, I'll feel guilty.
Jika aku tak bertindak, aku merasa bersalah.
Don't worry, it's nothing new.
Jangan cemas, itu bukan hal baru.
I'm used to being feared and loathed.
Aku biasa ditakuti dan dibenci.
How awkward.
Canggung sekali.
You put it back again.
Kau menaruhnya lagi.
It's not the right time yet.
Waktunya belum tepat.
Don't worry.
Jangan cemas.
I'll find the perfect time to do this,
Aku akan cari waktu yang tepat untuk melakukan ini,
to tell her how I feel.
memberi tahu perasaanku.
Tem. I told her your feelings.
Tem. Kuberi tahu dia perasaanmu.
It's Rouis!
Itu Rouis!
The lead in Adler?
Aktor utama dalam Adler?
He's handsome both on and off stage.
Dia tampan di atas dan di luar panggung.
His movements, his voice, his gaze.
Gerakannya, suaranya, tatapannya.
Rouis must be aware of what he's projecting every minute.
Rouis pasti tahu yang dia tampilkan tiap menit.
He's just a year older,
Dia cuma setahun lebih tua,
but he's the star of our club and holds power at school.
tetapi dia bintang klub kami dan berkuasa di sekolah.
What are you staring at?
Kau menatap apa?
Is being rude a wolf's habit?
Apakah serigala biasa kasar?
You're the pup from the art department.
Kau anak anjing dari bagian seni.
Perfect timing. I have a favor to ask.
Waktumu tepat. Aku perlu bantuan.
Follow me.
Ikuti aku.
Okay.
Baiklah.
So sorry, are you all right? The wind was too strong.
Maaf, kau baik-baik saja? Anginnya terlalu kuat.
You're fine, right?
Kau baik-baik saja, bukan?
I mean, guys always come to help you out.
Pemuda selalu membantumu.
The flowers were blooming beautifully...
Bunga berkembang dengan indah...
STUDENT ID - NAME: LEGOSHI CLASSIFICATION: CANIS LUPUS
KARTU PELAJAR - NAMA: LEGOSHI KLASIFIKASI: CANIS LUPUS
I'm fine.
Aku baik-baik saja.
I'm not at all bothered by whatever you do.
Aku sama sekali tak terganggu dengan tindakanmu.
How about finding a new room?
Kau mau cari kamar baru?
How ridiculous.
Konyol sekali.
Rabbit mattresses are so small.
Kasur kelinci sangat kecil.
What?
Apa?
I'll help you carry it.
Akan kubantu membawakannya.
You shouldn't. It's Haru.
Tak usah. Ini Haru.
Thank you. I can do it myself.
Terima kasih. Bisa kulakukan sendiri.
Three down... a marginalized animal?
Tiga menurun... hewan yang dibedakan?
One, two, three...
Satu, dua, tiga...
Ten letters.
Sepuluh huruf.
Hey, Sally. You could've stopped them if you were here.
Hei, Sally. Kau bisa hentikan mereka jika kau di sini.
She's pretty pissed at you.
Dia sangat marah denganmu.
You should stay quiet for a while.
Kau harus tak menonjol sementara waktu.
Thanks for your advice.
Terima kasih saranmu.
Wanna grab dinner?
Mau makan malam?
With you? No thanks.
Denganmu? Tidak usah.
Fine.
Baiklah.
Ten letters, a marginalized animal?
Dua belas huruf, hewan yang dibedakan?
Is it a carnivore?
Apa karnivora?
Black sheep.
Kambing hitam.
Black sheep... that's it!
Kambing hitam, itu dia!
You're so smart.
Kau pintar sekali.
Am I?
Begitukah?
Can I take a seat?
Aku boleh duduk?
Sorry, I'm waiting for my friend.
Maaf, aku menunggu temanku.
Is that seat open?
Kursi itu kosong?
The food's good even behind the cafeteria.
Makanannya lezat bahkan di balik kantin.
Impressive.
Mengesankan.
You're being ignored by the whole school, but you're still emotionally strong.
Kau diabaikan seluruh sekolah, tetapi secara emosional masih kuat.
Be careful, though.
Tetapi hati-hati.
We just had that incident.
Kita baru ada insiden itu.
It's dangerous for a rabbit like you to be alone.
Bahaya bagi kelinci sepertimu sendirian.
I lost my appetite.
Aku kehilangan selera makan.
Why don't you reconcile with your ex instead of badmouthing me around school?
Berbaikanlah dengan mantanmu alih-alih menghinaku di seluruh sekolah.
What? Who do you think you are?
Apa? Kau kira kau siapa?
Whose fault--
Salah siapa...
He's the one who suddenly kissed me.
Dialah yang mendadak menciumku.
Besides, I'm not interested in a guy
Lagi pula, aku tak tertarik dengan pemuda
who'd get so excited from a little peck.
yang bernafsu dari kecupan kecil.
Out of the way.
Menyingkir.
Listen up.
Dengar.
My ex and I are both endangered Harlequin rabbits.
Mantanku dan aku kelinci Harlequin langka,
We're out of your league.
Derajat kami jauh lebih tinggi.
You, an ordinary dwarf rabbit,
Kau, kelinci kerdil biasa,
ruined a well-bred couple.
merusak pasangan keturunan murni.
I'll tell the whole school you're flirting with other males.
Akan kuceritakan ke seluruh sekolah kau merayu pemuda lain.
Let's go.
Ayo pergi.
Rouis.
Rouis.
Fit his outfit before tomorrow's rehearsal.
Coba busana ini sebelum latihan besok.
What?
Apa?
Zoe is Tem's replacement.
Zoe pengganti Tem.
We made the decision in yesterday's meeting.
Kami membuat keputusan dalam rapat kemarin.
Right?
Benar?
Yes.
Ya.
"How ironic to see you here, Oddie the Water Spirit."
"Betapa ironisnya melihatmu di sini, Oddie Roh Air."
What?
Apa?
We're rehearsing. What's Oddie's line?
Kami sedang berlatih. Apa kalimat Oddie?
I'm sorry. I haven't memorized it yet...
Maaf. Aku belum menghafalnya...
Come on. Open your mouth.
Ayo. Buka mulutmu.
Rouis.
Rouis.
Hey. Did you eat up the script?
Hei. Kau makan naskahnya?
The only skill you goats have is to eat paper, isn't it?
Keahlian kambing seperti kalian cuma makan kertas, ya?
I'd rather you use that skill somewhere else.
Aku lebih suka gunakan keahlian itu di tempat lain.
I promise to have the lines by tomorrow.
Aku berjanji menghafalnya besok.
Rouis. Why is Zoe replacing Tem?
Rouis. Kenapa Zoe menggantikan Tem?
Tem and I were the last two at the audition--
Tem dan aku dua aktor terakhir di audisi...
-Knock first. -Yes.
- Ketuk dahulu. - Ya.
Go outside and learn the lines.
Keluarlah dan pelajari kalimatnya.
Yes.
Ya.
Hey. Why are you here? You're a nobody from the art department.
Hei. Kenapa kau di sini? Kau tak penting dari bagian seni.
Yeah. I'll leave, too, then.
Ya. Aku juga akan pergi.
No, you can stay here.
Tidak, kau bisa di sini.
Kai, make sure you get along with Legoshi.
Kai, pastikan kau akur dengan Legoshi.
You'll be working together in the art department.
Kalian akan bekerja sama di bagian seni.
What?
Apa?
You'll no longer serve as an actor.
Kau tak lagi menjadi aktor.
From now on, you'll be in the art department
Sejak saat ini, kau akan di bagian seni
and support us from backstage.
dan mendukung kami dari balik panggung.
Hey!
Hei!
Are you done stretching?
Kau sudah selesai rentangkan otot?
The spring performance act 2 footwork.
Gerakan kaki babak 2 penampilan musim semi.
The winter safari tournament's final dance.
Tarian akhir turnamen safari musim dingin.
You know better than anyone else that I didn't just mumble a spell.
Kau lebih tahu dari orang lain bahwa aku tak hanya gumamkan mantra.
Right, Kai?
Benar, Kai?
You've been an actor for two years, and what have you accomplished?
Kau sudah jadi aktor dua tahun, apa prestasimu?
Those two mistakes you made on stage.
Dua kesalahanmu di panggung.
Actually, I'm the one who'd like to ask.
Sebenarnya, aku yang mau bertanya.
Why did you think you could replace Tem?
Kenapa kau kira bisa gantikan Tem?
Actor's safety comes first.
Keselamatan aktor yang utama.
That's the crew's important job.
Itu tugas penting kru.
He's the lead, Kai.
Dia aktor utama, Kai.
Who the hell do you think you are?
Memang kau kira kau siapa?
This is just foolish.
Ini konyol.
I'll let you off the hook.
Aku akan biarkan kau.
Must be nice being rich.
Pasti asyik jadi kaya.
You'll be protected for the rest of your life.
Kau akan dilindungi seumur hidupmu.
What are you staring at?
Kau menatap apa?
Showing your fangs to avoid a fight?
Tunjukkan taringmu untuk menghindari perkelahian?
I'm surprised.
Aku terkejut.
You always act like a herbivore, but you had some ferocity within you.
Kau selalu bersikap seperti herbivora, tetapi ada keganasan dalam dirimu.
Excuse me.
Permisi.
Still, you seem like you have a good understanding.
Tetap saja, tampaknya kau punya pemahaman bagus.
Come.
Ayo.
We're sneaking into the auditorium tonight to give Zoe a rehearsal.
Kita menyelinap ke auditorium malam ini untuk melatih Zoe.
But if the school finds out...
Tetapi jika sekolah tahu...
That's why I need you to keep watch.
Itu sebabnya kau harus berjaga.
You're not going to refuse and act like a hero, are you?
Kau tak akan menolak dan bersikap jadi pahlawan, bukan?
That's too bad.
Sayang sekali.
If I promised you to give you my leg,
Jika aku berjanji memberimu kakiku,
you'd drool and accept my proposal, wouldn't you?
kau berliur dan menerima tawaranku, bukan?
You're a wolf.
Kau serigala.
Act like one and give yourself some prestige.
Bersikaplah seperti itu dan banggakan dirimu.
It's pretty dry now.
Kini sudah kering.
Males look at this face and think,
Pemuda melihat wajah ini dan berpikir,
"I want to protect her,"
"Aku ingin melindunginya,"
or "I need to be by her side,"
atau, "Aku harus mendampinginya,"
and approach me.
dan mendekatiku.
But when they find out that's an illusion, they mess around for a while and leave.
Tetapi saat mereka tahu itu ilusi, mereka bermain-main dan pergi.
I've been a prey my entire life.
Seumur hidup aku jadi mangsa.
Not that it matters, really.
Tetapi itu tak penting.
If this gets out, the drama club is doomed.
Jika ini ketahuan, klub drama tamat riwayatnya.
And I'll be... suspended?
Dan aku diskors?
Hurry up.
Cepat.
The teachers are on patrol more frequently since that incident.
Guru lebih sering berpatroli sejak insiden itu.
BACK ENTRANCE
PINTU BELAKANG
What are you doing here, little pal?
Sedang apa kau di sini?
I guess I should be asked that question.
Kurasa aku yang harus ditanya.
A herbivore.
Herbivora.
That's right.
Benar.
To conquer this world...
Untuk menguasai dunia,
you need to live by instincts.
kau harus mengikuti naluri.
I can't even get in the ring.
Aku bahkan tak bisa masuk ring.
You can just have me if you want.
Kau bisa makan aku jika mau.
But I want you to know
Tetapi aku ingin kau tahu
that even a pathetic animal like me had a reason to run away
bahkan hewan menyedihkan sepertiku punya alasan kabur
or cry out in fear.
atau menjerit ketakutan.
Would you understand?
Apa kau paham?
THE MOON AND THE BEAST
BULAN DAN BINATANG BUAS
Subtitle translation by Sayo Takada
Terjemahan subtitle oleh Mimi Larasati Bonnetto